all right good morning everyone I hope
you can hear me Alastair Campbell with
PASOK and welcome to our 31st annual
general meeting under unusual
circumstances we are still awaiting our
corporate secretary and so calling an
audible I think is the expression here
mr. chair I would suggest that perhaps
we guess like goes straight to your
remarks and my remarks and then we could
get on with the business component of
the AGM once our corporate secretary has
arrived does that make sense to you yes
so you wish me to go to my remarks as
the president then or is it n natori as
as chair I'll do mine okay and then
we'll we'll do the business section
after that does that make sense
alistair randy has dialed in Oh
fantastic
in that case never mind my audible let's
say transfer control over to a Glen and
you're in charge mr. chair great Thank
You Alastair certainly this is an
unusual moment in time for all of us and
first of all I want to welcome everyone
including the designated representatives
to the AGM and I'm Blaine Gibson I'll
chair the meeting as we've done in the
past we've invited the regulator's to
participate I'm not sure who's on the
call we were anticipating Vincent Savard
from AMF Rob O'Brien from BC FSA and
perhaps Frank Chong from BS British
Columbia FSA so we may get people in and
out as we unfold here today but just so
you're aware all the invite all the
regulators were invited to this so I'm
going to call the meeting to order
I asked Randy Bundys to be serve as our
secretary for the meeting and I've also
asked him to serve as a scrutineer and
today during the course of
this meeting I'm best Alistair who's our
president CEO to assist as well as
brandy Bundy and as you all know we've
all deeply impacted by the CB virus and
we are here today using zoom technology
which we hope is going to work quite
well I know there's been concerns
expressed both security and they seem to
be addressing that and I hopefully we're
not going to have anybody Zuma's today
out of the blue so we'll cross their
fingers on that one
Oliver me all of our members were
invited to join this meeting and said
were made were communicated in our
notice of the meeting for our AGM the
virtual environment is a bit of a
challenge so we have done some
pre-planning and to try to create an
effective process and we've prepared
with motions and second ders to
different things that are going to take
place today so if you are going to make
a motion please state your name fully so
it can be recorded in the minutes and
when I ask for a motion vote on the
motion
I'll ask for to be done orally if we do
get into a situation where there's a
formal vote required I'll ask each
designated representative who's on this
call to state their name and the number
of votes that they're authorized to cast
on their behalf of their company a
notice of the meeting was mailed to all
of the designated representatives on
March the 18th 2020 our scrutineer mr.
Bundys advises me that he has a
certificate on hand that proves it's
mailing and at this point I would
request a motion to dispense with the
reading of the notice and it take the
same as read mister
I move that the reading of the notice of
meeting be dispensed with and that the
same be taken as read sorry that was
Lynn Oldfield
Ryan if you're on the line I think we
were coming on you there he may be on
mute
perhaps if mark 10 is alive but maybe
you could second this is nothing we'll
hear and I was second this motion okay
everybody
you've heard the motion all the
designated representatives in favor
please signify by saying aye you'll have
to unmute a mute to do that I
those contrary if any signify by saying
no having not heard any contrary I
declare the motion carried I further
direct that a copy of the notice and the
certificate be kept with the records of
this means something nice let me unmute
there Randy pondus is our scrutineer I'm
advised by him that it at least 20% of
the designated representatives are
present by proxy at this meeting
so therefore direct that a copy of the
scrutineers report showing the actual
number of designated representatives we
have attendance today by proxy and the
percentage in aggregate of this number
represents of the total number of
designate eruption be kept in the minute
book of the corporation so regarding the
quorum and constitutional very meeting
as we do have 20% of the designated
representatives present representing a
quorum I now declare that the meeting is
regularly called and properly constitute
so having done all the back procedurally
on all matters today we will again a
verbal vote unless a ballot is demanded
if a ballot is demanded then members
will be entitled to cast their votes as
specified in a notice sent by the
corporation to each of the designated
representatives the order of events for
today's meeting were set forth in the
notice that we sent out for the AGM so
to begin the formal meeting today I
would ask Alastair Campbell our
president and CEO to assist me in
delivering a two-pronged approach for
reporting to the activities of the Board
of Directors I'll focus more on our
accomplishment since past year and
Alastair will focus on our priorities
for the upcoming year so as I said
earlier that's certainly we meet today
under very unusual circumstances and I
want to thank everyone for dialing in
here and participating our first virtual
AGM in our history I'm not sure it'll be
our last as we come out of this fog and
we embrace some changes and all the way
we all do business and I think when you
look at the virus itself and its impact
I'm a very big believer when you're
running a corporation and keeping your
steady hand on your mission billion and
values and when I look at mission of an
organization it to me it defines you
know what's the purpose of the
organization
you know why does the organization exist
when I look at this situation we're
Pasic and you know we're there to step
in and help mitigate disastrous
situations when an insurance company
fails and although we haven't had that
happen in a while we certainly are being
diligent about several situations and we
certainly when we when we look at what
can happen
I was kind of looking at you know if you
did get wind of the fact that your
insurance company had failed and you
were a policyholder and got a claim that
was in the works you know how are you
going to be feeling to get that new and
be fearful you're going to be worried
about the impact and when I look at the
elements that exist today with the virus
impacting us it reflects to me I'm just
really how important it is for us to get
it right when that big moment comes and
again it reflects on much of the journey
that alistair has led pastic on this
past year and and also on into the near
future with the priorities that we're
setting as an organization we've worked
very closely with our corporate
secretary randy Bundys for today's
meeting to make sure the legal niceties
and being looked after so that this
virtual session is fully legitimate and
randy has a deep institutional memory
sure there's no precedent for what we're
doing today so it's a long way of saying
you know we may have a few glitches
today along the way and just bear with
us and we thank you again for
participating this past year for Pasic
as being an essential component of our
insurance industry infrastructure we
began this journey 15 years ago with
Paul Kovac Sen and also we had our chair
laurie savage who stepped down last year
after 14 years on the board
both of them have provided outstanding
support to both myself and to our new
CEO Alastair Campbell this past year
from an industry perspective many of you
on the line know better than me but 2009
was a frustrating year for the market
and you know gross premiums icing digit
rates of growth relative inflation the
industry la Surrey was didn't improve at
all for some and we also saw him loss as
a crime property end of things and this
has left a large number of companies
that had underwriting losses and 2019
also saw a number of carriers who were
extending prior year underwriting losses
into the O 19 years so we've been
monitoring a lot of these activities at
basics and then we'll talk about the
purl committee later today but certainly
we've been active with several
situations and working closely with the
management team it like our board has
tackled a number of unusual but
significant initiatives this year the
most was obviously the review the
coverage and benefits which was our
priority for 2019 and I think the last
time this was touched or looked at was
14 years ago Alistair is going to give
you an update on status of this
situation and I would like to say before
I turn it over to him that myself for
sure and the board are very pleased at
how management is work to gain
perspectives from key stakeholders
including consumers and regulators and
brokers job engagement of the
stakeholders active listening getting it
right before we bring things to the
board for for a vote and this hard work
has really paid off I think in and so
when we look at going into 2020 when we
looked at putting it into when they are
prior issue was starting with the
publication of a really important
research
paper which was entitled alternative
liquidation
exploring K thing
Canada's Property and Casualty
resolution toolkit and/or man if it's
work really hard to actually be and as
we seek to ensure that Pasic will
continue to be able to honor its policy
holder protection when it's needed on
the operational side of things at PASOK
we've modernized our administrative
assessment framework that's now
incorporating a risk rating and we've
ensured adequate funding for our
operations in a consolidated industry
with their left at play now we've also
invested resources in modernizing our
contingency planning and REM mat and a
colder commute although is a new social
media world the next stage of this is
going to involve deeper engagement with
our regulators our Pro Committee which
is our pre-insolvency regulator liaison
committee is comprised of our CEO and
our independent directors we've been
actively liaison with key regulators
most notably Aussie and AMF in Quebec
we've been looking at scenario modeling
and contingency planning and and one
we'll be expanding this us other
jurisdiction in Canada as we sort of
gain some experience on what it's going
to look like we continue to engage the
industry through a risk officers form
our emergency risks and webinars and our
quarterly newsletter solvency matters we
want to explore best practices around
Canada in the world and and we have
particularly mission in seeing what
we've learned from the international
form of insurance guarantee schemes and
that is an organization alistair is now
going to be serving as your is serving
at sir
so that's been very interesting to hear
what's going on in Europe where they
have active insolvencies underway and
there's certainly things we can learn
from what's emerging there and Alistair
is a great conduit for us to learn more
their basics also been working
diligently on raising industry awareness
for the significant risk of what happens
if a large earthquake was to take out a
major urban center in Canada and we've
identified options that could help
mitigate the material tail risks for our
industry in our country Canada is the
only significant developed nation in the
world
with a material quake exposure that does
not have some form of industry backstop
mechanism that is a very significant
statement our board is designed
mitigating systemic risk as a permanent
priority issue for Pasic management
until such time as we can get a
satisfactory resolution I want to thank
the small management team for the large
volume of quality work we received over
the last year I'm amazed at just what's
coming out of this small working group
and I'm amazed at the energy of Alistair
and his team and how they have pushed me
down the road and engaged me on just so
many different things it's been it's
been a real experience and a real
learning experience for me as well and I
think that the team has really bonded
around Alistair style and has aggressive
to do get things done attitude and I
think we all benefit from that I also
want to thank the members of the board
for their professionalism and their
dedicated to our mission this past year
they've made my year plays they say very
rewarding and I have every confidence
that we are in very good hands with our
management team and that we will
continue to strengthen our ability to
protect consumer
ended he's ahead you know there's an old
saying that I use and I didn't invent it
but its proper planning prevents poor
performance I think that Alistair
certainly has helped us move in that
direction and I think we're very much
further down the road than we were
twelve months ago on what we need to do
as an organization to be ready for that
chance to dance if something goes bad in
our inner country
so having said that Alistair I will turn
that over to you Thank You Glen and
thank you for those kind words let me
start by thanking all of those who have
joined us in person or remotely for
today's meeting these are challenging
times for Canada and the world and we've
done our very best to ensure we can
perform our corporate legal obligations
today in a way that best ensures the
health and safety of all involved I'd
like to say a few things about PASOK and
I work over the past year and I thank
you for your patience in and your
interest first of all it's safe to say
the three-part mission of PASOK was
successfully achieved in 2019 we can
confidently claim that no consumers
suffered undue hardship as the result of
an insurance solvency ii absence of any
new insolvencies meant that the cost to
insurer's were certainly minimized in
fact we began 2019 by successfully
completing the process of returning 21
million dollars to our insurer members
this song representing the final amounts
recovered from the active estates of all
previously failed insurers in Canada
finally confidence in the pnc industry
among consumers remains high a recent
survey indicates they have no concern
about the solvency of their own ensure
that the industry in general as we've
just seen from a recent events in the
world
consumer views can change rapidly so we
have to keep that very much in mind the
work of PASOK intensified this year on a
number of fronts our priority issue for
2019 was the formal review of our
coverage and benefits which Glenn just
referenced we engaged our members by a
working group and broadened that
industry engagement to include formal
process both with IBC and with I back we
completed this portion of the work by
issuing an industry consultation paper
with ten preliminary recommendations
based on three guiding principles
fairness transparency clarity and
modernization and then we went on to
survey our entire membership on their
views we were very pleased that more
than 83 percent of the Canadian market
responded to that survey member input
combined with industry feedback and the
results of qualitative and quantitative
consumer market research propelled us
well for the dialogue we then initiated
with the Canadian Council of insurance
regulators their response enabled us to
complete a comprehensive stakeholder map
and enabled passuk management to table
final recommendations at our November 20
1914 after exhaustive discussion and
debate our board approved the most
significant changes to coverage and
benefits since 2006 these changes
include an increase in the personal
property limited to $500,000 and an
increase in automobile and commercial
limits to $400,000 the board also
decided to increase the unearned premium
amount to $2,500 while retaining a 70
percent copay obligation meaning a
maximum individual payout on unearned
premium of 1,750 dollars the passing
board also approved a fixed review date
in future requiring a review of coverage
and benefits every five years and
committing that the next review
conducted in close collaboration with
CCIR would take place within 36 months
amongst other approved changes some
broadening of coverage in line with
proposals made by our colleagues at
Anglia IBC as well as some other
technical adjustments to our model
including plain language definitions for
covered lines intended to improve the
clarity and transparency of
communication with the consumer
finally our board formally asked CCIR to
publicly join IBC and PASOK in calling
upon the Government of Canada to create
some form of backstop mechanism to
address the systemic risk associated
with a mega quake in DC or the Montreal
Ottawa corridor our 2020 priority issue
is expanding PASOK's resolution to look
at key to this work we'll be moving to
institutionalize our working
relationships with AMF and Asti as well
as BC FSA where we have now signed
intervention protocols and moving to
establish such intervention protocols
for the other provinces also important
is continuing to flesh out the mandate
and working practices of our new
pre-insolvency regulatory liaison
committee the Perl Committee made it up
entirely of our independent directors we
began to socialize this important work
around resolution to a meeting with the
IBC board of directors and by a series
of workshops at the National Insurance
Conference of Canada and in 2020 we have
now begun executing on our comprehensive
four-part action plan for this priority
issue now PASOK remains seized by the
critical importance of addressing the
risk of systemic contagion potentially
caused by a major earthquake we engaged
with IBC and Finance Canada constantly
on this topic two of the year and remain
disappointed that we have not been able
to make greater progress we have made
strikes to align with CCIR and I back in
this important cause and we intend to
renew our efforts on this issue in 2020
now that the federal election is over
historically pass explored is limited
management's mandate to a single
priority issue each year given the
limited resources at our disposal
however recognizing the urgent priority
to address this systemic risk topic our
board has designated
getting systemic risk as a permanent
priority issue until such time as we
secure the required resolution
accordingly we will be redoubling our
efforts to address this issue and will
not rest until we have achieved success
I might add that the experience that
Canada is undergoing around pandemic
amplifies the compelling case to have an
in case of emergency break glass fully
prepared action plan to deal with tail
risk events pandemic is one quake is
another and we have a compelling
argument to make now that it is time to
address this systemic exposure looking
out beyond 2020 we've already begun work
on our four designated priority issue
for 2021 contingency planning and
desktop simulations we're working much
more closely with key regulators never
before and now have early warning
regarding potentially distressed
insurance this means we now have the
opportunity to engage more proactively
in crisis management simulations where
pre-planning might assist in ensuring
more effective response to worst-case
scenarios when they actually happen
finally we've been asked by our board to
start thinking strategically about Pasek
brand awareness we have begun by seeking
to engage with IDC and I back in a more
structured and sustained way and it
we've expanded our industry awareness
through the publication of our solvency
matters newsletter who are highly
successful risk officers fora and
through an increased number of public
speaking engagements but over the course
of the coming year we will be giving
more thought to ways that we can ensure
all market facing players in our
industry have a better awareness of the
passing value proposition and can make
that value more visible to Canadian
consumers I just like to conclude by
saying I have found the first year in
this role both challenging and deeply
rewarding I sincerely appreciate the
engagement from our board and I'm
particularly grateful for the coaching
and guidance I've received from our new
board chair Glenn Gibson I've also
benefited immensely from a highly
engaged in
a professional team I have inherited
here a PASOK we've accomplished a lot in
this year and look forward to achieving
even more in the pursuit of our mission
in 2020 and beyond thank you for your
patience with all of that happy to turn
the con back to our chair Glen Gibson
thank you I will pause for a moment to
see if there's any questions coming out
of that questions anyone nothing heard
I'll carry on I wish to point out that
the report of the board includes the
audited statements of the corporation
for the year end December 31st 2018
these statements were sent to all
members member companies as part of our
annual report and it was sent along with
their notice regarding this meeting
these statements don't require a
resolution by members they are there for
your information only I'm going to ask
Samir Chaudhary from KPMG today to read
the certificate as to the audited
financial statements thank you I'm just
checking whether people can hear me okay
okay so this is the report that
accompanies the audited financial
statements of hazard we have audit of
the financial statements of the property
and casualty insurance compensation
cooperation which comprised the
statement of financial position as at
December 31st 2019 the statement of
comprehensive income for the year then
ended the statement of changes in equity
for the year and ended the statement of
cash flows for the year that ended and
notes to the financial statements
including a summary of significant
accounting policies sure enough to
referred to as the financial statements
in our opinion the accompanying
financial statements present fairly in
all material respects the financial
position of the entity as at December
31st 2019 and its financial performance
and its cash flows for the year then
ended
in accordance with international
financial reporting standards we
conducted our audit in accordance with
Canadian generally accepted auditing
standards our responsibilities under
those standards of further described in
the responsibilities for the audited
classes the inception of our auditors
report we are independent of the entity
in accordance with the ethical
requirements that are irrelevant to our
audit of the financial statements in
Canada and we have fulfilled our other
ethical responsibilities and accordance
with these requirements we believe that
the audit evidence we have obtained is
sufficient and appropriate to provide a
basis for our opinion management is
responsible for the preparation and fair
presentation of the commercial
statements in accordance with
international financial reporting
standards and for such internal control
as monitoring determines is necessary to
enable the preparation of the statements
that are free from material misstatement
but the due to fraud or error in
preparing the financial statements
management is responsible for assessing
the entity's ability to continue as a
going concern disclosing as applicable
matters related to going concern and
using the going concern basis of
accounting
unless management in either intensity
liquid identity or to cease operations
or has no realistic alternative but to
do so those charged with governance are
responsible for overseeing the entity's
financial reporting process our
objectives are to obtain reasonable
assurance about whether the financial
statements as a whole are free from
material misstatement whether due to
fraud or error and to issue an auditors
report that includes our opinion
reasonable assurance is a high level of
assurance but it's not a guarantee that
an audit conducted in accordance with
Canadian generally accepted auditing
standards will always detect
MTM statement when it exists
misstatements can arise from fraud or
error and are consolidate and a
considered material if individually or
in aggregate they could reasonably be
expected to influence the economic
decisions of users taken on the basis of
the financial statements as part of an
audit in accordance with Canadian
generally accepted auditing standards we
exercise professional judgment and
maintain professional skepticism
throughout the audit we also identify
and assess the risks of material
misstatement of the first statements
whether due to fraud or error designing
to form or the procedure responsible
wrists and obtain ordered evidence that
is sufficient and appropriate to provide
a basis for her opinion the risk of not
detecting a material misstatement
resulting from fraud is higher than for
one result from error as fraud may
involve collusion forgery intentional
emissions misrepresentations or the
override of internal control we obtain
an understanding of internal control
relevant to the audit in order to design
order procedures that are appropriate in
the circumstances with not for the
purpose of expressing an opinion on the
effectiveness of the entity's internal
control the evaluate the appropriateness
of accounting policy is used and the
reasonableness of accounting estimates
and the related disclosures made by
management we conclude on the
appropriateness of management's use of
the going concern basis of accounting
and based on the ordered evidence
obtained whether a material uncertainty
exists relates to events or conditions
that may cost significant doubt on the
entity's ability to continuous is going
concern if we conclude that a material
observed exists we are required to draw
attention in our auditors report to the
related disclosures in the financial
statements or if such disclosures are
inadequate to modify our opinion our
conclusions are based on the audit
evidence obtained up to the data for
auditors report however future events or
conditions may cause the integer C's to
continue as a going concern we evaluate
the overall presentation structure and
content of the financial statements
including the disclosures and whether
the financial statements represent the
underlying transactions and events in a
manner that achieves fair presentation
we communicate with those genres of news
regarding
among other matters the plan scope and
timing of the audit and significant oil
findings including any significant
deficiencies internal control that we
identified cheerin or audit that brings
me to conclusion of the report
thank you very much we are now going to
move on to the election of directors
pursuant to bylaw number one the
directors are to be elected from
individuals nominated by the board of
directors and by any designated
representative who follows a written
nomination with the secretary not less
than five days prior to this meeting the
secretary has informed me that there
were no written nominations filed for
the election to the board so the
following twelve directors were
nominated by the board for election as
directors pursuant to paragraph 29 bylaw
number 1 Martin Balu of intact Financial
Corporation Alastair Campbell of paci
SEC Andrew Cartmel Saskatchewan
government insurance
Briony stop Red River Valley mutual
insurance company Christian portray with
a capital general insurance company glen
gibson of the GTG group david McNaughton
who is a consultant Heather Masterson
travelers Canada David Oakton who's a
consultant Lynn Oldfield who is with AIG
Insurance Company of Canada Bruce
Thompson who is a consultant and finally
Peter Walker who is with Aviva Canada
anyone we elect as a director at this
meeting will hold office until our next
AGM which will be in 2021 particulars of
those who have are nominated were
included with the information letter
which accompanied our notice of the AGM
the individuals we nominated constitutes
a complete slate of directors I would
ask for a motion for the nominations to
be closed
we're looking for a heavy right thing so
I my apologies
I am gin for us to approve Andrew
Cartmel I snuck in that motion you have
heard the motion all designated
representatives in favor please signify
by saying aye Louis contrary if any
signify by saying no not hearing any
knows I declare the motion carried as
the motion has passed there are a number
of nominees for position I declare the
nominees to be duly elected directors of
the corporation to hold office in
accordance with the bylaws until our
next AGM or until their successors are
elected or appointed our next order of
business is the appointment is the
appointment of the auditors I would ask
for a motion by a designator
this is math table year I moved at KPMG
Chartered Accountants Toronto Ontario be
appointed auditors of the corporation to
old office until the next annual meeting
of members or until their successors are
appointed and that their remuneration be
fixed by the board of directors Peter
Walker I second that motion
you've heard the motion all designated
representatives in favor please signify
by saying aye aye aye hi
those contrary if anything those
contrary of any signified by saying no I
declare this motion carried we now move
to approving the actions of the board of
directors and officers of Pasic I would
ask someone to move that all acts
contracts proceedings appointments the
elections and payments enacted made and
taken by the directors and officers or
the corporation since our last G AGM of
members as the same are set out or
referred to in the minutes of the
meetings of the board of directors of
corporation be approved and confirmed
this is Lynn Oldfield mr. chairman
pleased to make such a motion
Brian seems to have a problem Martin are
you are a backup guy here yes I will
second that motion
thank you you've heard the motion all
designated representatives in favor
please signify by saying aye
those kind of any signify by saying no
sorry those country and he knows not
hearing any I declare this motion
carried I would ask if there's any new
business to be brought forward to
today's meeting not hearing any I would
ask for a motion to terminate the
meeting this is Massimo year mr. chair I
move that the meeting be terminated
Peter Walker I second that motion
Peter Walker yeah
can you hear me gloom yes oh yeah Peter
emotion thank you you've heard the
motion all designated representatives in
favor please signify by saying aye those
contrary if any signify by saying no
having heard none I declare the motion
carried and the AGM is now terminated
I'm now going to invite Ian Campbell who
is our vice president of operations with
Pacey
to provide an overview of the paper why
insurers fail and why insurers fail and
lessons learned from the failure of the
reliance insurance company thanks very
much mr. chair this is our 14th
publication of why insurers failed it's
a serious research series we started in
2007 an original research series for
PASOK and we're very proud of this and
we use our annual general meeting as an
opportunity to launch the report to the
industry and with us this report we
always seek to tell a very interesting
story I think we've got a good one this
year I look at ourselves as cold-case
detectives for the PLC insurance
industry so this happened back in 2001
and events decades prior to that our
race in the reports so wait I think
you'll find it a very good read it's a
presentation of the facts a about a very
significant consultancy and the value
add that we bring here is we talk about
the causes of the insolvency and the
lessons learned for both insurers and
for regulators and I'm wondering there's
pressure on my colleague grant Kelly I
know he's out there and he's watching
this presentation now he and I alternate
each year to write the why insurers
failed reports so the moment that I
finish going through this report the
countdown clock starts on a grass report
for next year so 365 days start my very
last word
this morning so where pressures on you
okay the first slide so why this white
of all insurers this insure this was the
largest us insurance Alton C ever it had
a negative surplus of 1.1 billion
dollars when the company went bust in
2001 and we heard from guaranty funds in
the states in June 2019 payouts now
total well over four billion dollars
this includes claims payments and
administrative expenses the next largest
failure to put things in perspective was
Lygia an insurance company in 2002 and
the extent of damage there was one point
two billion dollars the impact of
changes in a company's risk appetite is
is striking in this report you had a
company here that had a very solid
history careful acquisitions they built
a business on Ernie four years
very steady growth attentive
underwriting and all of a sudden under
new management there was a market change
in the risk appetite of the organization
we're gonna talk you'll see later on
about flaws in the corporate structure
and the governance of this insurance
company essentially the the Board of
Directors was a club heavily conflicted
very self-serving and unchanged for
years and years there was a lack of
independence to challenge management
decisions on any front and there was a
very dramatic change in the capital base
in english' in the short space of three
years in mid-1998 the company had a
record net worth of 2.3 billion dollars
in in October 2001 when it became
insolvent it was posting a negative
surplus of 1.1 billion dollars there is
a similarity with this report to two
other insolvencies that took place
that same year one of them I wrote up
back in 2018 that is lessons learned
from the failure of H I H Insurance
Limited in Australia that firm had an
asset deficiency of between three point
six billion dollars and five point three
billion dollars and there was also
independent insurance in the UK where
there were irregularities in claimant
claims accounts that caused that
insurance company to go bankrupt
interesting thing about this this report
too
these three companies each of them was
led by an industry maverick a person
that as CEO was exerting undue influence
or over the organization the companies
were operating with flawed business
strategies and there were very intent on
gaining market share from larger
competitors in the industry also unique
about this case is this was a
liquidation of a solvent Canadian branch
reliance Canada a very unique situation
to think about it it's a fourth closure
of a profitable firm the parent company
went bankrupt the operation in Canada of
fully fully profitable but forced to
close now finally the novel approach
that we as an organization took to
resolve this situation fastly pledged
its assessment power in this game
comfort to the liquidator to quickly
process claims and everybody avoid the
time and expense of a traditional
assessment to the industry I could ask
you an all-star to go to the next slide
and that's a background on all right the
next slide is a background on reliance
insurance company so the story begins in
Philadelphia back in 1817 a 184 your
history with this organization that it
originally started as the Volunteer Fire
Association of Philadelphia grew to the
27th largest largest insurer in the u.s.
a very sizable firm 8,000 employees
13,000 shareholders 350 million dollars
in revenue and a hundred million dollars
in capital reserve it was a national
insurer with a full range of product
lines from basic property and auto to
special Alliance including workers comp
non-standard auto and professional
liability it grew steadily over the
years through acquisitions careful
acquisitions and those were put on hold
in the late 1960s when the the firm
endured quite an over property losses
uncontrollable events hurricanes and
also the he was dealing with property
losses from the race riots in 1967
things changed in our next slide slide 3
is with Saul Steinberg in leasco he's a
protagonist in our story a young and
highly ambitious individual and would
play a key role in the in the future of
reliance insurance company
was born in Brooklyn New York in 1939
attended the Wharton School of Finance
he was graduate with a background in
economics and during his time there he
studied he was really obsessed with the
IBM business model of leasing he did a
paper and titled the decline and fall of
IBM which is highly misleading because
he was quite enamored with the success
of IBM and their leasing of large
mainframe computers it was always on his
mind when he graduated he established
the ideal leasing company he was just 22
years old he had $25,000 at seed money
from his father and established that
firm and it was intent on leasing
computer hardware essentially taking
products taking IBM computers that too
were coming off line and leasing them
back into the industry and taking
advantage of some of the tax write-offs
in 1963 with the firm idea leasing
reported one point eight million dollars
in revenues and this grew to seventy
four million dollars in assets and eight
hundred employees by 1967
very very sizable growth that led to a
number of acquisitions he was really
intent on acquisitions he bought up the
CTI container transport International
and grew this jointly with his computer
leasing and the world's largest
container I'm sorry the cargo container
transportation company jointly so it was
a mixed bag he really didn't care as
long as the ferns were profitable it was
kind of a dog's breakfast of what he put
together computer leasing and cargo
containers but it it was working for him
and he was always on the search in
search of new acquisitions Disney and
Chemical Bank caught his interest he was
very shrewd and ambitious no company was
too large to interest him and he had a
number of failed bids along the way
those are two other companies that he
pursued but to no end if you google Saul
Steinberg
one of the things that comes up is green
mail as a source of profits he was big
on this he was one of the performance of
this he had a reputation for hostile
takeover this but never actually
completed one yet a very simple formula
for success and that's to attract
investors to take over a company
pressure the company to cut costs and
almost appear reckless and when the
board essentially management fights back
he would sell off the accumulated stock
at a profit he did exactly this with
Disney and made himself 58 million
dollars he threatened to fire the board
of Disney and sell off all the cartoon
characters to the highest bidder
so it was ruthless sinister but also
very very profitable it's a kind of an
evil genius
look he had on life slide number four
Edward neder is another person that
figures prominently in our story
he was a Wall Street financial analyst
with Carter Burland and what Ben wheel
he had this visionary concept of
creating a large financial services firm
he penned a very obscure client report
entitled the financial services holding
company and essentially this challenged
the the central tenets of the
glass-steagall Act of 1933 that it was
possible for non-financial holding
companies to takeover of a financial
firm and transfer an insurance company's
unallocated surplus to the unregulated
holding company they they were then free
to invest the assets back in the
organization or maybe in other
enterprises not necessarily related to
the insurer he predicted back then the
early at a very early stage the
emergency of large all-encompassing
financial services firms and this
non-financial holding company model
could overcome investment hurdles such
as the glass-steagall Act which required
the separation of US banking insurance
investment and industrial company
operations so Edward never read in his
report came up with the terms redundant
capital and surplus surplus essentially
he looked at pnc insurance practices
family were highly conservative and they
produced reserves exceeding regulatory
requirements so it was very very
attractive for for takeover Biltz or
they were takeover builds sorry bids
unlocking value for investors he saw
great potential here ambitious
diversified companies essentially they
could marry with fire and casually
insurance companies and and cease their
redundant capital it's almost like a
dowry they looked at it they looked at
it like so Steinberg brought netter in
as an adviser to help look for insurers
that could produce strong balance sheets
and a surplus capital he looked at him
for identification of suitable
candidates and they were always very
careful not to name the companies that
they were looking to take over because
this could lead to start price
stimulation and management opposition so
what they did they actually were using
actresses names to name the companies
such as Marilyn Monroe and Greta Garbo
they had code words to Marilyn and Greta
in going through and talking about the
target firms that they were after so
reliance Edward knitter earned a
finder's fee of $750,000 for
recommending reliance finally to to Saul
Steinberg as a takeover target slide
number five and now we just look at this
see development under Steinberg his
guidance how the organization evolved
over the coming decades I took a decade
at a time and they look for major events
happening during that decade in the
1970s he was carrying a very huge dead
load
there was a 1968 takeover of reliance
insurance the insurance company who was
very successful it was debt financed an
unsolicited takeover bill they were four
hundred million dollars in stock was
issued to fund the deal and essentially
this is really remarkable because leasco
took over a company ten times his size
and that gave it access to 125 million
dollars of capital and the key focus
here for Steinberg in the 1970s was
structural and operational change it was
a challenging decade for him mentioning
this company's huge debt all of a sudden
he's strapped with and so he one thing
he changed the name from release Co I
started from leasco to Reliance group he
wanted to be known as a financial
services firm and get away from the the
leasing handle and he established you'll
see it on the meso we'll come to that in
a second but he established a
holding company arrangement reliance
financial was established as an
intermediate holding company and he also
established sister organizations
reliance consulting and reliance
development which looked after real
estate and this would be the
organization organizational framework
that would guide them forward for years
an issue came up in 1970s for Steinberg
and that is Moore's Law Gordon Moore the
Intel Corporation co-founder had a
theory that computer power doubles every
two years due to advances in hardware
technology and Steinberg was late to
learn this he was heavily invested in
each computers and found that with the
rapid advances and IBM going to market
with later and more powerful products he
was now sitting on millions and millions
of dollars of computers that nobody
wanted to rent the struck stock price
subsequently plunged at very dramatic
plunge in 1975 and was a very terrible
time for the company but he also saw
opportunity in this there was an
opportunity to buy back shares so he
used company funds to buy back shares
from angry investors and that helped him
to increase the total shares that he
controlled in the organization the slide
number six will show us the corporate
structure for his holding company
arrangement its Elster if you could just
advance one there real good
so this you're not seeing there you will
see it in the in the printed report or
the report that we're going to post on
the passing website but there are 22
organizations underneath reliance
insurance company where I've just kind
of done a cutaway so I've kind of locked
off the the the head of the beast here
and this is the arrangement that they're
very very solid nothing changed here
over the years he had a coulding sorry a
holding company up talk called RGH
reliance wholly reliance group holdings
and then he had three sister
organizations and really Reliance
financial was the did all the heavy
lifting here so there was reliance
development and Reliance consulting at
the same level but it was Reliance
financial that was the intermediate
holding company and the conduit for
profits firm reliance
transferred up in in form of dividends
to rallyin Reliance financial and then
up to the RGH and that was
controlled RGH was controlled by the
Steinberg family sorry 47% so when there
were dividends going forward they were
going right into his pocket he was
paying himself first the 1980s was a
represented refocus and business
strategy of a change in strategy the
organization became very active
worldwide they're active in every state
50 states and 50 countries they're both
near and far they were in Puerto Rico
Guam Virgin Islands Mexico Asia Europe
Brazil and Canada reliance group
holdings there was there were changes
there to lock down control so there was
a reorganization of the board Steinberg
inserted his father his brother and
several close friends on the Board of
Directors a very dysfunctional board
three of the directors served on the
board for 16 years many of the directors
were officers and always internal
directors outnumbered external directors
so he was very insulated in terms of
protection from management and any
negative feedback he he might get in
terms of direction over the organization
he was using junk bonds to fund all the
acquisitions and that was just leading
to a huge huge debt leveraged
acquisitions millions and millions of
dollars in debt he hired the nation's
leading financiers Michael Milken from
Drexel Burnham Lambert and company the
junk junk bond King was brought into the
fold and it always put pressure on
reliance insurance gonna be down at the
bottom to be profitable and to transfer
the dividends upward this was very
critical to the success of the house of
cards that he had built saw lived a very
lavish lifestyle and that's he was a
real Playboy one of the best paid
executives in the US he had a 29 room
mansion on Long Island
he had a sprawling 80 room Park Avenue
apartment built by the Rockefellers in
the 1930s he was a big fan of old
masters paintings and flew around in a
private jet with bedrooms in the jet and
he threw parties for himself where he
had gorgeous women dress up to model
some of the old masters paintings to
recreate the paintings in real life
at some of his party so he's really
living to excess with other people's
money and the decade closed with a
crisis close close to the end of the
decade there's pressure on reliance the
large volume of dividends flowing to RDH
to service the massive debt that had to
keep coming reliance the start value
plummeted due to the stock market crash
in 1987 there were property losses from
natural disasters that decade the 1989
San Fran earthquake and fierce price
competition in the marketplace so he
closed the decade with the establishment
of Reliance national and this would be a
firm that would focus on non-traditional
risks and that becomes very very
important in the 1990s the problem with
very ambitious growth and started ugly
in the 1990s said there was a hiccup to
start the decade the collapse of Drexel
Burnham Lambert Michael Milken going to
jail convicted for securities law
violations and the disappearance of the
junk bond market there the organization
made very significant investments abroad
in Europe Asia Africa and Latin America
and there were 21 companies you didn't
see in that corporate framework I just
showed previously but 21 organizations
shows you the depth of the expansion of
the organization and RGH at this point
the parent country was 900 million
dollars in debt by the end of 1994 and
he was found himself in the 1990s unable
to pursue the investments he warned in
Pennsylvania adopted the model Holding
Company Act governing the operations of
holding companies and the acquisitions
of insurers by non non insurers and also
the Department of Justice was looking
into acquisitions that lessen
competition in the marketplace so this
really constrained his ability to to
flex his muscles with acquisitions
he was reliance was under pressure in
this marketplace for higher
profitability and a decision was made in
1991 to exit personal lines in favor of
specialty lines of coverage and they
were now focusing on unique exposures
two-thirds of the business was coming
from this nuclear power plant coverage
environmental disasters earthquake
exposed construct
chemical manufacturers professional
liability workers comp iris drivers
health and transit years 1995 to 2000
were the final years for the
organization he was riding high in the
middle of the decade the value of the
organization 2.3 billion dollars was a
ha a high point 3.4 billion in revenue
twelve point eight billion in assets 1.7
billion a statutory surplus 585 million
our profits but there were problems
brewing on several fronts
during that decadent I talked about the
dividend transferred in that in those
space of five years 1995 to 1999 166
million dollars was transferred from
reliance insurance companies up to the
Steinberg family at the top but there's
a whole confluence of negative
developments in the 1990s especially in
1995 to 2000 that essentially killed a
company those were negative underwriting
results in the high risk in specialty
lines there was soft market price
competition very aggressive marketing by
competitors and heavy losses on the non
standard auto product reliance was
involved with a eunuch of her scheme
this was a reinsurance fronting scheme
and essentially it was it was used to
pool to to pool shares a workers
compensation risk and Reliance a very
significant exposure here they were
heavily invested in workers comp in 1997
there was a California decision there
also factored in with h IH insurance
limited to two cause them to be quite
unprofitable and it affected Steinberg
here as well it allowed for more claims
and allowed the the claims to be
retroactive so essentially 50% of the
reliance premiums were coming from
workers comp and general liability and
they were not pricing those products
properly because this was made
retroactive so they were kind of caught
in the lurch they got involved with
various very extremely risky investments
very poor investment results 92% of
their portfolio invested in junk bonds
and one technology stock in 1999 which
gives people pause for forethought there
and also a a 52
term debt financing which at the end of
2000 really caused a cash crunch for the
organization essentially short-term
short-term debt was increasing by 50%
and the senior notes and debentures dude
were down by 34 percent I think that is
shown in slide 10
okay that's given in transvestite the
dividend transfers this shows
essentially if you look at the the bars
in blue were the dividends flowing up to
Reliance insurance companies from all
its subsidiaries and the red was the the
transfer from Reliance to the rth on the
top so you see that RGH essentially
could not be profitable unless or
without reliance being involved here so
quite a huge transfer and very reliant
in nineteen eighty eight ninety nine and
two thousand and now the next slide I
think is shows the there we are
outstanding dead you see how the
long-term death is decreasing in the
short term debt is increasing and it's
all coming to a head in the year 2000
when there was a really big cash crunch
slide twelfth we talked about regulatory
intervention this paper looks at several
early warning signs that were perhaps
missed by regulators I mean I'm going
back in time and relying a public
information available at the time it's
really hard to pinpoint and say
definitively that the Pennsylvania
insurance Department dropped the ball on
this but certainly there were signs that
there was trouble for the organization
the insurance regulatory information
system test ratios for 1995 to 1999 test
number three for Reliance showed sudden
and sustained double-digit increases in
the policies written they were gaining
market share in a soft market and likely
this was coming from inadequate pricing
rather than pricing out the products
that they already had customers they
already had they were trying to attract
new customers with lower prices test
number eight the liabilities to liquid
assets test is an early indicator of
financial trouble there were failing
that test and also test number twelve
the estimated current reserve deficiency
they failed from 1997 onward
and finally shareholder dividends
requiring regulatory approval people
were questioning that allowed in the the
trade presses how was reliance getting
away with this especially when you add
it all up 166 million dollars in space
of five years to the family and some of
that had to be approved by the
regulators so how was that done how
could that be approved cash flow became
an issue in August of 2000 the
Pennsylvania insurance company a
certainty of Pennsylvania insurance
Department stepped in to oversee the the
dividends and disbursements for reliance
that require detailed financial
information and business plans and
proposed material transactions and
proposed material transactions on
November 2000 relized a faltered on five
hundred and thirty eight million dollars
of lungs and the their surplus was
sharply decreasing and also
policyholders were coming forward with
new claims which further do that through
that down because they were worried
about the future of reliance and they
thought we'd better get our claims in
now there was a downward spiral in the
stock price beginning in June 1998 and
it was fed by bad credit ratings and
negative press and it was just a slide
right down to zero until the the firm
was delisted on linear at stock exchange
in December of 2000 in January of 2001
on January 29th a formal supervision was
ordered the Pennsylvania insurance
department installed permanent overseers
to manage reliance operations in April
21st or sorry April 1 of 2001 reliance
said their 2000 financial statements
were not complete and they reported a
surplus of 624 million dollars and it's
now to a negative 220 sorry now it's
negative 220 million in May of 2021
there was a rehabilitation order
executed reliance was ordered to produce
a financial statements for two thousand
and they found that the they came
forward with unaudited financial
statements and shown the surplus now of
negative 730 million dollars so they
lost five hundred and ten million
dollars in 11 months and think you're
just getting worse
September 1st the q1 for 2001 the
financial statements showed a surplus
now of over one point billion dollars in
in the in the red a very bad situation
and getting worse
they were hemorrhaging cash reinsurance
recover Bulls were 60% of Reliance's
cash flow and this was slowed down
obviously because at the at the time the
911 the World Trade Center attacks which
caused serious cash flow problems with
lots and lots of reinsurance and finally
October 30 2001 a liquidation order came
through killing the company the
aftermath of this is on slide 13 thank
you
mid 1998 we saw they were on a high of
2.3 billion dollars and a stunning
reserve reversal of fortunes a net worth
of 1 point 1 billion dollars negative
just three short years later very
significant job losses massive
investment losses and big cost to the
industry missus felt both at the
personal level with workers losing jobs
on severance pay and also at the
corporate level with banks and
bondholders losing very significant
investments up to seven hundred million
dollars there 187 instead 187,000
outstanding claims at the time of the
insolvency when it was declared
insolvent there were seven thousand
pensioners left with pensions
underfunded to the tune of a hundred
million dollars and our colleagues at
the National Conference of insurance
guaranty funds confirmed that eighty
thousand claims made their way through
into us PNC guaranteed funds and as I
mentioned earlier as of June 2019 those
claims those payos guarantee fund
payouts they stated four point four
billion dollars this is is a battle
opera and it's a two-part story if if
this is a drama we looked at this as act
two with Reliance Canada was active in
the Canadian marketplace since 1918 you
know in all lines property are pretty is
certain property accident and sickness
Auto boiler and machinery fidelity
liability and maturity they specialized
in professional liability for lawyers
engineers architects dentists and
Hospital programs directors and officers
liability pollution and of our
liability product liability very
established in the marketplace in August
of 2000 us to recognize what was going
on in the US and froze the assets of
Reliance Canada and directed its to stop
writing new business in early 2001 when
the Pennsylvania Insurance Department
stepped in with the liquidation order on
the 3rd of October Asti responded just
two days later on October 5th seize
control of the assets and this was due
to financial difficulties with the
parent company they set up an immediate
ring fence to keep the assets in Canada
they cited a need for immediate action
here that the US Court was likely to a
force of transfer of the surplus any
surplus funds in Canada to the US the
company lacked funds to cover any
material increases in gross liability in
Canada there was concern about current
liabilities being perhaps underestimated
here and also uncertainty about the
collection of reinsurance with what was
going on in the states with the 9/11
travesty we looked we passed assigned a
loan and serve loan and services
agreement with the liquidator we
borrowed from the canadian estate of
reliance canada with funds repayable
only of dividends from the state were
less than 100 percent
we passive was was required to provide a
50 million dollar covenant from the
compensation fund or assessment capacity
to secure the agreement with the
liquidator the number recovery on claims
was a hundred percent so we weren't
required to advance funds this was a
very unique approach we pledged our
assessment power and that enabled a
liquidator to provide adequate comfort
to pay stake holder claims immediately
they'd otherwise be personally liable
for any preferential payments if the
estate was unable to pay claims fully
this took pressure off the assignment of
claims and facilitated faster payment of
policy order holder claims and it also
spared people other insurance companies
here in the marketplace in Canada like
this it spared members the time and
expense of a traditional assessment to
deal with this insolvency the liquidator
here had trouble closing the file
encountered complexities with both the
insurance sorry the reinsurance and the
evaluation of liabilities it took 17
years to close to 5
reinsure has demonstrated a reluctance
to accept the assignment of reinsurance
there were delays in the collection of
reinsurance proceeds and there were
class and crown actions against Rothman
Benzes Benson & Hedges Inc an imperial
tobacco company limited the liquidator
had struck tentative agreements Sunday
to court approval with those
organizations and attempts to settle
were not approved by the court to do the
intervention of Quebec class-action reps
and also create its re8 crowns that were
suing the tobacco companies directly
that didn't want to be bound by broad
language wording in any war of rulings
the court found here that crowns are not
bound by the war they winding up in
restructuring act they can pursue
separate and direct action against the
tobacco companies under separate
legislation this kind of set up a
dilemma for the liquidator here in
Canada catch-22 situation and that's why
it went on so long the file remained
open indefinitely while they tried to
bring this to a close
eventually the claims were transferred
to Westport and 104.7 million dollars of
surplus was transferred to the u.s.
liquidator the paper also looks at a
class action or serie a case study of
the home insurance company I want to
thank my colleague Jim Harris who penned
this case study which has been inserted
in this case study because it is very
relevant and it's a parallel situation
there's us parents that became insolvent
in June 2013
winding up order was issued for home
insurance Canada two weeks later and
this organization was already in the
process of winding down operations since
mid-1990s they were writing only
commercial insurance at the time and
soul of professional lines 14 years
earlier they sold them off so this was a
very solvent insurer and it had net
assets of thirty nine thirty nine
million dollars no questions about this
and there was a short-term loan services
agreement signed with the liquidator
we had to pledge ten million dollars of
general assessment capacity and finally
that was resolved in four months long
term the business was transferred to
Lombard it was a good commercial result
for stakeholders
the prompt sale and transfer a business
and no need to assess passive passive
members in just a couple more slides the
causes of the reinsurance insolvency in
our situation the insurer here was very
focused on growth at all costs
net Breton net premiums written grew by
16% on average between 1996 and 1999 it
was in very risky lines of business and
this was a very big gamble for reliance
its pricing was very very aggressive as
supported it was done so to support a
very ambitious growth strategy rapid
growth in a soft market is a sign of
under priced products there was a faulty
and dysfunctional governance structure
decisions were often made to benefit the
Steinberg family it had exerted 47%
control over the organization the board
was static it was conflicted it was
passive and lacking independence
reserving was inadequate reliance
significantly underestimated future
claims cost some of it was wasn't their
fault necessarily with the workers comp
but still that was the situation they
had to deal with and they were overly
optimistic perhaps with some of their
their pricing and reserving the
investments very very risky
they were focused in below
investment-grade bonds and stocks and
immersing worsening credit and a
deteriorating market for lower great
debt made it very difficult to refinance
the debt and all that came to a head in
in the year 2000 now finally Capital
Management reliance found himself unable
to refinance its debt it had difficulty
managing its capital surpluses were
continually depleted by shareholder
Givens and passed forward to RGH a
possible contributing factor is
regulatory supervision that yes the
Pennsylvania insurance department acted
to decisively when it was very
clear that reliance was in deep trouble
but I did mention some early warning
signs and perhaps those were overlooked
lessons learned we draw from this this
is almost like a run don't run with
scissors type situation reserving
adequate prevail
for outstanding exposure are critical to
the financial health of any insured with
underwriting it's important assessing
and properly pricing risks is vital to
an insurance company's long-term success
if you're entering new markets companies
should exercise caution when doing so
and entering new lines of business with
acquisitions and joint ventures they
should support the strategic objectives
of the organization and not necessarily
be drawn in just because they're
profitable but not a good fit with the
family of companies financial statements
we saw here was an issue for Reliance a
company's financial statements must
accurately reflect its truth financial
position director responsibilities
boards of financial institutions must
demonstrate independent judgment in
capital management maintaining capital
strength is very important for the
success of the success of any insurer
and lessons for regulators regulators
must show healthy suspicion and be
prepared to intervene at the very first
sign of trouble and with wara wara and
other solvency legislation we found it
this really the situation exposed the
fact that we relaxed language to blame
the crown and that is an issue the final
a second last slide is expanding
passionate PASOK's resolution toolkit
the resolution of Reliance Canada and
the home insurance Canada situation both
demonstrate that the fact is successful
actions can be taken by passing without
the need to assess the industry it
amplifies the need for closer
examination of creative resolution
options these resolutions are early
launch points for more study in this
area this is PASOK's good our 2020
priority issue it's a good hook to talk
about what we're doing this year it
shows the difference perhaps that being
the focus could be on early intervention
versus a traditional liquidation and it
prompts us to look at the sale the
transfer and the reinsurance of books of
business and not necessarily just paying
when things go bad and ultimately our
goal will always be to enhance consumer
protection reduce cost to the industry
and strengthen policyholder confidence
in the industry my final slide I think
it's just that's a copy of the I want to
give a shout out to our
operations manager de Nica Paul let's
prepare the book great layout and do a
thorough job on this we'll be posting
this on the website we do have copies
and we will make available upon request
we can send those to you happy to do
that
every member company will be getting
printed copies mailed to them but in the
meantime you're going to want to read
this and we will post this right after
the meeting and get that up for you to
read I think you're gonna find it very
enjoyable read so do hope you enjoy that
and thanks very much for your patience
with this and your patience with our
online meeting so back over you Alistair
Thank You Ian and thank you to all
participants for your engagement in the
31st annual general meeting and pasok to
the members of our board who are
planning to join us for our next meeting
it begins in four minutes and so you
will need to log out of this session and
log into the next zoom meeting
invitation thank you all for your
engagement today